<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: side-project | cjwebb.github.io]]></title>
  <link href="http://cjwebb.github.io/blog/categories/side-project/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://cjwebb.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-15T20:22:57+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://cjwebb.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Colin Webb]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Virtues of Side Projects]]></title>
    <link href="http://cjwebb.github.io/blog/2016/06/15/the-virtues-of-side-projects/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-15T11:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://cjwebb.github.io/blog/2016/06/15/the-virtues-of-side-projects</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I write software for a living, and most of my side projects are software based too. I view side projects as a tool for learning. Learning by doing.</p>

<h2>Side projects can feed positively into your day job, as you learn new skills and techniques</h2>

<p>Building things from scratch, and by yourself, means you have to broaden your knowledge base. If you&rsquo;re writing a website, you&rsquo;ll need to know how to deploy it, how to enable database backups, how to configure a firewall, and basic server maintenance tools.</p>

<p>When I first started a side project, I wrote Java all day, and developed on Windows. I knew hardly anything about Linux, and certainly had no experience running a server. Whilst it wasn&rsquo;t necessarily all fun, I learnt a lot that has been widely applicable later on in my career.</p>

<p>Side projects can also assist in your day job directly. An example of this very happened recently to me. A couple of colleagues were pair programming on an adjacent desk. They were stuck on something, and casually asked if I knew how to fix a problem they were having. After a minute or so looking at the code, my answer was “Yeah, I did something like this recently in my side project”. I then sent them a link to my side project on Github, and after adapting my code, they had solved their issue and were away coding again.</p>

<p>Usually it&rsquo;s skills and techniques that will transfer over from side-projects. Occasionally, you can just copy some of your side project code.</p>

<h2>Side projects let you experiment without adversely affecting your day-job</h2>

<p>Want to learn Haskell? Great! But don&rsquo;t then deploy it at work, and <strong>force</strong> other people to maintain your code.</p>

<p>Want to try out a theory about structuring an object-orientated codebase? You can, and if it doesn&rsquo;t work out, you won&rsquo;t have annoyed all of your colleagues.</p>

<p>Having a great job, or working on a great team, means that you&rsquo;re given time to learn or embrace different technologies or techniques. However, if you&rsquo;re not that lucky, side projects can give you the freedom to learn and experiment in ways you wouldn&rsquo;t normally be allowed to.</p>

<h2>Side projects can die without negative consequences</h2>

<p>If you get bored with working on a side project, just stop working on it. A project with paying customers is not a side project. Nobody can honestly expect you to keep working for free on something you find boring.</p>

<p>Work on something different for a while. If the side project doesn&rsquo;t interest you again, forget about it, and thank it for the experience and skills you gained whilst working on it.</p>

<h2>Side projects can force you to think differently</h2>

<p>Compared to your day job, side projects are subject to a different set of constraints. Different constraints means different problems to solve. Your decisions will be different as a result of this.</p>

<p>The main constraint on my side projects is money. At most places I&rsquo;ve worked, the budget is usually huge in comparison to what I can set aside. EC2 instances costs nothing to a corporation, but ~$50/month, multiplied by three for redundancy and replication, soon make a dent in my own finances.</p>

<p>This constraint has also led me to use a lot of free-tiers of hosted-database providers. If a company is willing to provide me with free services, then I&rsquo;m all ears. This was how I was introduced to NoSQL databases, and I gained a completely different perspective on how to store, and query, data.</p>

<h2>Side projects count as experience</h2>

<p>Always be learning. There is a famous quote by Malcolm Gladwell about how doing something for ten thousand hours can help achieve mastery. Whilst this quote is often <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/IAmA/comments/2740ct/hi_im_malcolm_gladwell_author_of_the_tipping/chx6ku3">out of context</a>, everyone understands that you need to practice something in order to become better at it. The good news, is that you can practice your skills whilst working on a fun side-project.</p>

<p>The second piece of good news, is that you can often use side projects as direct evidence to show off to potential employers. I&rsquo;ve often chatted about my side projects whilst being interviewed, and I&rsquo;ve often chatted about interviewees' side projects whilst I interviewed them. They&rsquo;re a great way to showcase your talents!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
